Hello everyone, welcome back to EnglishPod.
大家好，欢迎回到EnglishPod。
My name is Marco.
我是Marco。
And I'm Erika.
我是Erika。
And today we're going to be bringing you another great sports lesson.
今天我们要给大家带来另一节精彩的体育课。
Yes, this one is for all our hockey fans.
是的，这节课是献给所有冰球迷的。
I know we have a lot of listeners from Russia, so this is a very popular sport in Russia,
我知道我们有很多来自俄罗斯的听众，冰球在俄罗斯非常流行，
Czech Republic.
捷克共和国。
Yes, and Canada.
是的，还有加拿大。
And Canada, right?
还有加拿大，对吧？
Very, very popular in Canada.
在加拿大非常非常流行。
It's our national game.
这是我们的国球。
Well, I guess because you guys have so much ice.
嗯，我猜是因为你们那里冰太多了。
I know, there's nothing else to do.
我知道，也没别的事可做。
Because skiing and hockey.
因为滑雪和冰球。
All right, so it's going to be a really fun lesson.
好了，这将是一节非常有趣的课。
We're going to have a lot of great vocabularies.
我们会学到很多很棒的词汇。
So before we start in the dialogue, let's take a look at vocabulary preview.
所以在开始对话之前，我们先来看看词汇预览。
Vocabulary preview.
词汇预览。
Well, we have three words for you now.
嗯，我们现在有三个词要讲。
The first one, really simple, puck.
第一个，很简单，冰球。
Puck.
冰球。
P-U-C-K.
P-U-C-K。
Puck.
冰球。
So it's almost like duck, but with a P. And this is actually kind of like the ball that
它听起来像duck，但开头是P。这其实就是冰球运动中用的那种球，
you use in hockey.
但又不是球。
But it's not a ball.
但它不是球。
It's flat.
它是扁平的。
And round.
而且是圆的。
So it looks like a disc, kind of like a mini frisbee.
所以它看起来像个圆盘，有点像迷你飞盘。
And this is what the players do.
这就是球员们做的事。
This is what they...
这就是他们...
They chase this around.
他们追着这个跑。
They chase it, right.
他们追着它，对吧。
So in basketball, you have a ball.
在篮球里，你有球。
In soccer, you have a ball.
在足球里，你有球。
In hockey, you have a puck.
在冰球里，你用的是冰球。
Okay, our next word.
好的，下一个词。
Key game.
关键比赛。
A key game.
So this word, key.
所以这个词，“关键”。
Important.
重要的。
It means important, right?
它的意思是重要的，对吧？
Really important.
非常重要的。
Yeah.
是的。
So I can say a key game is a really important game.
所以可以说，关键比赛就是非常重要的比赛。
Exactly.
没错。
You could also maybe say a key player.
你也可以说关键球员。
Key player is a really important player.
关键球员就是非常重要的球员。
Or even a key goal.
甚至关键进球。
A key goal.
关键进球。
Okay.
好的。
So let's take a look at our last word now.
现在我们来看最后一个词。
Finals.
决赛。
The finals.
So the finals are the last games.
所以决赛就是最后的比赛。
That's right.
没错。
And the winner of the finals wins the championship.
决赛的胜者赢得冠军。
Okay.
好的。
For example, in the World Cup in soccer, there's only one game played in the finals.
例如，在世界杯足球赛中，决赛只有一场比赛。
So after everyone gets eliminated, there's one game where the winner is the champion.
所以当所有队伍被淘汰后，就剩一场比赛，胜者就是冠军。
Yes.
是的。
Okay.
好的。
So now we're ready to listen to our dialogue.
现在我们准备好听对话了。
And it's going to be a little bit faster than usual.
它会比平时快一点。
Because it's a sports commentator, right?
因为这是体育解说员，对吧？
And it's exciting.
而且很激动人心。
And there's a lot of action.
有很多动作场面。
So don't worry about it.
所以别担心。
Listen to it.
听一听。
And then we'll come back and talk about some of the vocabulary.
然后我们再回来讨论一些词汇。
Hello, everyone.
大家好。
I'm Rick Fields.
我是里克·菲尔兹。
And here with me is Bob Copeland.
和我一起的是鲍勃·科普兰。
Howdy folks.
大家好，朋友们。
And welcome to today's game.
欢迎收看今天的比赛。
You know, Rick, today's a key game between Russia and Canada.
你知道，里克，今天是俄罗斯队和加拿大队的关键比赛。
As you know, the winner will move on to the finals.
如你所知，胜者将晋级决赛。
That's right.
没错。
And it looks like we're just about ready to start the match.
看起来我们马上就要开始比赛了。
The ref is calling the players for the faceoff.
裁判正在召集球员进行争球。
And here we go.
比赛开始了。
The Russians win possession and immediately start up their attack.
俄罗斯队赢得球权，立即发起进攻。
Fedorov gets checked hard into the boards.
费奥多罗夫被重重地撞到了板墙上。
Boris Richal has the puck now.
鲍里斯·里查尔现在控球。
And he passes it to center.
他把球传到了中路。
He shoots.
他射门了。
Wow.
哇。
And it's going to be a goalie.
这球要变成守门员了。
All right.
好的。
The puck is back in play now.
球现在重新回到比赛中。
Pavel Bory is on a breakaway.
帕维尔·博里单刀突破。
He is flying down the ice.
他飞快地滑过冰面。
The defenders can't keep up.
防守队员跟不上。
Slapshot.
大力击射。
He scores.
他进球了。
What an amazing goal.
多么精彩的进球啊。
All right.
好的。
So the Canadians versus the Russians, huh?
所以加拿大队对阵俄罗斯队，是吧？
It reminds me of a classic, classic game.
这让我想起了一场经典的比赛。
Exactly.
没错。
The classic match.
经典的对决。
So, let's take a look at some of the vocabulary that we heard in the dialogue in Language
那么，让我们来看看对话中听到的一些词汇，在“语言
Takeaway.
要点”部分。
Language Takeaway.
语言要点。
We have five phrases in Language Takeaway today.
今天“语言要点”部分有五个短语。
And the first one is face-off.
第一个是“争球”。
Face-off.
“争球”。
So, Marco, a face-off here is a noun, right?
所以，马可，这里的“争球”是名词，对吧？
It's a noun, exactly.
没错，是个名词。
And it's...
而且它是……
So, in the beginning of a match, the two players will stand face-to-face, right?
所以，在比赛开始时，两名球员会面对面站着，对吧？
That's why it's called kind of a face-off.
这就是为什么它被称为“对峙”或“开球”。
And the referee will drop the puck and they'll try to get it.
然后裁判会放下冰球，他们会试图抢到它。
Exactly.
没错。
So, that's the face-off.
所以，那就是“开球”。
That's the face-off.
那就是“开球”。
Yeah.
是的。
Okay.
好的。
Let's take a look at our next word.
我们来看看下一个词。
Check.
阻挡。
To check.
进行阻挡。
So, an interesting verb here, hey?
这里有个有趣的动词，是吧？
Yeah, it's really interesting because it's different from the way that you would say
是的，它真的很有趣，因为它和你通常说的
check or revise, right?
“检查”或“修订”不一样，对吧？
Yes.
是的。
This is actually kind of a violent move.
这实际上是一种有点暴力的动作。
Yeah.
是的。
So, what do you do?
那么，你是怎么做的？
So, basically, in hockey, you take your body and you hit another person with it.
基本上，在冰球中，你用身体去撞击另一个人。
Okay.
好的。
So, to check someone is to hit them with your body.
所以，“阻挡”某人就是用身体去撞击他们。
With your body, right.
用身体，没错。
You can't use your arms or your legs or your hands.
你不能用胳膊、腿或手。
You can only hit them like with your shoulder or your hip.
你只能用肩膀或臀部去撞他们。
Yeah.
是的。
It's called a hip check.
这叫做“臀部阻挡”。
Okay.
好的。
So, yeah.
所以，是的。
It's very cool.
这很酷。
All right.
好的。
Our next word, goalie.
我们的下一个词，守门员。
Goalie.
守门员。
A goalie is a person.
守门员是一个人。
Right.
对。
Who is probably the bravest of the hockey match.
谁是冰球比赛中最勇敢的人？
No kidding.
没开玩笑。
So, why don't you tell us what the goalie does?
那么，你为什么不告诉我们守门员是做什么的？
The goalie prevents the puck from coming in the net.
守门员阻止冰球进入球网。
From going into the goal, right?
阻止它进球门，对吧？
Yeah.
是的。
So, the goalie stops the other team from getting a goal.
所以，守门员阻止对方球队得分。
A goal.
得分。
Yeah.
是的。
Okay.
好的。
So, the goalie prevents the goals.
所以，守门员阻止进球。
All right.
好的。
Very interesting.
非常有趣。
Now, our fourth word is related to goalie.
现在，我们的第四个词与守门员有关。
Yes.
是的。
Save.
扑救。
That's a noun, right?
那是个名词，对吧？
It's a noun here.
这里是个名词。
So, the goalie makes saves.
所以，守门员做出扑救。
That's right.
没错。
When he stops a goal, he makes a save.
当他阻止进球时，他就做出了一次扑救。
Makes a save, right?
做出扑救，对吧？
Yeah.
是的。
Okay.
好的。
We have some examples so we can understand this form of using save.
我们有一些例子，这样我们就能理解这种使用“扑救”的形式。
Yes.
是的。
Example one.
例子一。
That was an unbelievable save.
那是一次难以置信的扑救。
Example two.
例子二。
The goalie didn't make the save.
守门员没有做出扑救。
Example three.
例子三。
What a save!
多棒的扑救啊！
The Russians win!
俄罗斯队赢了！
Yeah, a little bit unusual here that save is a noun instead of a verb, but I think those
是的，这里“扑救”作为名词而不是动词有点不寻常，但我认为那些
examples were helpful.
例子很有帮助。
Mm-hmm.
嗯哼。
Now, let's take a look at our last word, breakaway.
现在，我们来看看最后一个词，breakaway。
Breakaway.
Breakaway。
Okay, so you have two words there that we know already.
好的，这里有两个我们已经认识的词。
Break.
Break。
Yes.
是的。
Right?
对吧？
And away.
还有 away。
Yeah.
嗯。
So what do these two words together actually mean?
那么这两个词组合在一起到底是什么意思呢？
Well, imagine a group of hockey players all fighting to get the puck, right?
嗯，想象一下一群冰球运动员都在争抢冰球，对吧？
And then one player breaks off, breaks out of the group.
然后一个球员脱离出来，冲出人群。
Escapes.
逃脱了。
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
对对对。
And he skates down the ice and he has the puck.
然后他滑过冰面，拿到了冰球。
And he's far away from the other players.
他离其他球员很远。
Right, right.
对，对。
So he's going away from the other players by himself.
所以他独自一人远离其他球员。
Yeah.
嗯。
Okay, so breakaway.
好的，所以是 breakaway。
Mm-hmm.
嗯哼。
All right.
好的。
So we've looked at a lot of hockey language here.
我们在这里看了很多冰球术语。
Yep.
是的。
And I think it's time now to listen to our dialogue again.
我想现在是时候再听一遍我们的对话了。
This time we're going to slow it down a little bit.
这次我们会放慢一点速度。
Yeah, I think this will help you to understand these words a little bit better.
是的，我觉得这能帮你更好地理解这些词。
Hello everyone.
大家好。
I'm Rick Fields and here with me is Bob Copeland.
我是 Rick Fields，和我一起的是 Bob Copeland。
Howdy folks and welcome to today's game.
大家好，欢迎收看今天的比赛。
You know, Rick, today is a key game between Russia and Canada.
你知道，Rick，今天是俄罗斯和加拿大的关键比赛。
As you know, the winner will move on to the finals.
如你所知，胜者将进入决赛。
That's right.
没错。
And it looks like we're just about ready to start the match.
看起来我们马上就要开始比赛了。
The ref is calling the players for the faceoff.
裁判正在召集球员进行争球。
And here we go.
比赛开始了。
The Russians win possession and immediately set up their attack.
俄罗斯队赢得控球权，立即展开进攻。
Fedorov gets checked hard into the boards.
Fedorov 被狠狠地撞到了板墙上。
Moisei Shad has the puck now and passes it to the center.
Moisei Shad 现在拿到冰球，传给了中锋。
He shoots.
他射门了。
Wow, what a save by the goalie.
哇，守门员扑救得太精彩了。
All right.
好的。
The puck is back in play now.
冰球现在重新回到比赛中。
Pavel Burei is on a breakaway.
Pavel Burei 正在单刀突破。
He is flying down the ice.
他飞快地滑过冰面。
The defenders can't keep up.
防守队员跟不上。
Slapshot.
大力击射。
He scores.
他得分了。
What an amazing goal.
多么精彩的进球啊。
OK, this dialogue is interesting because we have commentators narrating or describing
好的，这段对话很有趣，因为解说员在叙述或描述
what's happening.
正在发生的事情。
Yeah.
是的。
In that moment, right?
在那一刻，对吧？
Yeah.
是的。
And they're using some interesting grammar, aren't they?
他们用了一些有趣的语法，不是吗？
Exactly.
没错。
They are because some actions are happening in that moment.
是的，因为有些动作正在那一刻发生。
But we noticed something a little bit strange.
但我们注意到了一些有点奇怪的地方。
All right.
好的。
Let's look at it in Grammar Breakdown.
让我们在语法解析部分看看。
Grammar Breakdown.
语法解析。
OK, let's listen to this sentence that we previously heard in the dialogue.
好的，我们来听听之前在对话中听到的这句话。
Moisei Shad has the puck now and passes it to the center.
Moisei Shad 现在拿到冰球，传给了中锋。
He shoots.
他射门了。
Moisei Shad has the puck now and passes it to the center.
Moisei Shad 现在拿到冰球，传给了中锋。
He shoots.
他射门了。
I noticed that he's using the present simple, right?
我注意到他用了现在时，对吧？
Yeah.
是的。
So even though the action is now, it's in present simple.
所以即使动作发生在现在，也是用一般现在时。
Yes.
是的。
Even though the action is happening in that moment, he's not using the present progressive
即使动作正在那一刻发生，他也没有用现在进行时
or the present continuous.
或现在进行时。
This is because if you notice, the actions are very, very brief.
这是因为如果你注意的话，这些动作非常非常短暂。
And fast.
而且很快。
And exciting.
而且很激动人心。
Exactly.
没错。
So you don't really have enough time to say, for example, he is shooting.
所以你没有足够的时间说，比如，他正在射门。
Yes.
是的。
Because it's only one quick action.
因为那只是一个快速的动作。
He shoots the puck very fast.
他非常快地射出了冰球。
Right?
对吧？
Or for example, you wouldn't really say, he is passing.
或者比如，你不会说，他正在传球。
Yeah, he is passing the puck.
是的，他正在传球。
Right.
对。
It's just one quick action.
只是一个快速的动作。
He takes it and passes it.
他拿到球然后传出去。
And the action is finished.
动作就结束了。
Yes.
是的。
I think we can see a few more examples of this.
我想我们还能看到更多这样的例子。
Let's listen again.
我们再听一遍。
The Russians win possession and immediately set up their attack.
俄罗斯队赢得控球权，立即展开进攻。
Here, we can hear that he is using the present simple again.
这里，我们可以听到他又用了现在时。
Because these are very short actions that finish quickly.
因为这些是非常短暂、快速完成的动作。
Right?
对吧？
Exactly.
没错。
And it's actually very, very common when you're describing something you see that's happening
实际上，当你描述你看到正在发生的、非常激动人心的事情时，
now, that's really exciting.
这是非常常见的。
It's common to use present simple.
用一般现在时很常见。
Exactly.
没错。
If you pay attention, most sporting events are in the same way.
如果你注意的话，大多数体育赛事都是这样。
They would describe the actions that are happening in the present simple.
他们会用一般现在时描述正在发生的动作。
Not present progressive.
而不是现在进行时。
Yeah.
是的。
But Marco, you have an example of some present progressive here, right?
但是 Marco，你这里有一个现在进行时的例子，对吧？
Yes.
是的。
Let's listen to this sentence.
我们来听听这句话。
He is flying down the ice.
他正在冰面上飞驰。
Now we heard the sentence, he is flying down the ice.
我们听到了这句话，他正在冰面上飞驰。
Right?
对吧？
Now this one is in progressive.
这句用的是进行时。
Yeah.
是的。
Why is that?
为什么呢？
Well, first of all, when we say he's flying down the ice, it's not that he's literally
嗯，首先，当我们说他正在冰面上飞驰，并不是说他真的在飞。
flying.
飞。
No, he's not an airplane.
不，他不是飞机。
He's just skating really fast.
他只是滑得非常快。
Right?
对吧？
So we kind of exaggerate and we say, oh, he's flying down the ice.
所以我们有点夸张地说，哦，他正在冰面上飞驰。
But he's actually skating.
但实际上他是在滑冰。
So this is a progressive action.
所以这是一个进行中的动作。
He is doing it.
他正在做这件事。
It's happening for more than one second.
它持续了不止一秒钟。
Yeah.
是的。
Exactly.
没错。
So that's why we would say, he is flying down the ice instead of he flies down the ice.
所以这就是为什么我们会说，他正在冰面上飞驰，而不是他飞驰在冰面上。
Yes.
是的。
Right?
对吧？
He's skating really, really, really fast.
他滑得非常非常非常快。
Yeah.
是的。
Okay.
好的。
So here we see that sometimes in English, we do use present simple to talk about what's
所以我们看到在英语中，有时我们会用一般现在时来谈论正在发生的事情。
happening now.
正在发生的事情。
Right?
对吧？
When it happens really, really quickly or when we want to show that it's really exciting.
当它发生得非常非常快，或者当我们想表明它非常激动人心时。
Exactly.
没错。
Yeah.
是的。
Makes it much more exciting if we just use the present simple.
只用一般现在时会让它更激动人心。
Yeah.
是的。
Okay.
好的。
Let's listen to this exciting dialogue one more time and we'll come back and talk a little
让我们再听一遍这段激动人心的对话，然后回来再聊一会儿。
bit more.
一会儿。
Hello everyone.
大家好。
I'm Rick Fields and here with me is Bob Copeland.
我是 Rick Fields，和我一起的是 Bob Copeland。
Howdy folks and welcome to today's game.
大家好，欢迎收看今天的比赛。
You know, Rick, today's a key game between Russia and Canada.
你知道，Rick，今天是俄罗斯和加拿大的关键比赛。
As you know, the winner will move on to the finals.
如你所知，胜者将进入决赛。
That's right.
没错。
Looks like we're just about ready to start the match.
看起来我们马上就要开始比赛了。
The ref is calling the players for the face off and here we go.
裁判正在召集球员进行争球，比赛开始了。
The Russians win possession and immediately start up their attack.
俄罗斯队赢得控球权，立即展开进攻。
Fedorov gets checked hard into the boards.
Fedorov 被狠狠地撞到了板墙上。
Maurice Richart has the puck now and he passes it to Sender.
Maurice Richart 现在拿到冰球，传给了 Sender。
He shoots.
他射门了。
Wow.
哇。
What a save by the goalie.
守门员扑救得太精彩了。
All right.
好的。
The puck is back in play now.
冰球现在重新回到比赛中。
Pavel Bure is on a breakaway.
Pavel Bure 正在单刀突破。
He is flying down the ice.
他正在冰面上飞驰。
The defenders can't keep up.
防守队员跟不上。
Slap shot.
大力击射。
He scores.
他得分了。
What an amazing goal.
多么精彩的进球啊。
All right.
好的。
So hockey is the Canadian national sport.
所以冰球是加拿大的国家运动。
Well, actually it isn't the national sport.
嗯，实际上它并不是国家运动。
Yeah.
是的。
What is it?
那是什么？
Lacrosse.
长曲棍球。
Yeah.
是的。
But anyway, we're not, we don't have a lesson about lacrosse today.
但不管怎样，我们今天没有关于长曲棍球的课。
Not yet.
还没有。
No.
不。
But actually all Canadians love hockey.
但实际上所有加拿大人都热爱冰球。
Like we start playing hockey when we're about two years old.
比如我们大约两岁就开始打冰球。
Yeah.
是的。
I've heard that some Canadian children learn how to skate before they learn how to walk.
我听说有些加拿大孩子学走路之前就学滑冰了。
It's totally common.
这很常见。
Well, it is a great sport.
嗯，这是一项很棒的运动。
Very, very exciting.
非常非常激动人心。
It's very fast paced and it's very aggressive.
节奏很快，而且非常激烈。
That's what I like about it.
这就是我喜欢它的原因。
I know.
我知道。
Not violent, but very aggressive.
不是暴力，但非常激烈。
Yeah.
是的。
But you know what?
但你知道吗？
I must tell you that I am not a good Canadian.
我必须告诉你，我不是一个好加拿大人。
You're not a hockey fan?
你不是冰球迷？
No, I'm not.
不，我不是。
Really?
真的吗？
Yeah.
是的。
I really, I really hate hockey.
我真的，真的很讨厌冰球。
Why?
为什么？
You know what?
你知道吗？
It's so small.
它太小了。
It's hard to see where it is on the ice and it's cold and these guys are fighting and
在冰上很难看清冰球在哪里，而且天气很冷，这些家伙还在打架，
anyway.
总之。
Have you ever been to a hockey game?
你去看过冰球比赛吗？
Yeah.
看过。
Many times.
看过很多次了。
And I just find that the puck is really small.
我就是觉得冰球太小了。
Maybe you just need better seats.
也许你只是需要更好的座位。
Maybe.
也许吧。
Well, what do you guys think about hockey?
嗯，你们对冰球有什么看法？
We'll post some videos and some pictures of hockey on the comment section so you can more
我们会在评论区发布一些冰球的视频和图片，这样你们可以
or less see a little bit more about this really interesting sport and tell us what you think
大致多了解一点这项非常有趣的运动，然后告诉我们你们的想法。
about it.
是的。
Yeah.
And you can also check out our website, EnglishPod.com and you'll find some interesting stuff about
你们也可以访问我们的网站 EnglishPod.com，那里会有一些关于
hockey, right?
冰球的有趣内容，对吧？
Exactly.
没错。
And also lots of other great lessons.
还有很多其他精彩的课程。
Exactly.
没错。
And also if you have any questions or doubts about the lesson, you can leave your questions
如果你们对课程有任何问题或疑问，可以在网站上
on the site.
留言。
All right.
好的。
We're out of time.
我们时间到了。
We'll see you guys next time.
下次再见。
Thanks for listening and goodbye.
感谢收听，再见。
Bye bye
拜拜。